1-6. Write a program to count blanks, tabs, and newlines.
1-7. Write a program to copy its input to its output, replacing each string of one or more blanks by a single blank.
1-8. Write a program to replace each tab by the three-character sequence >,  backspace, -, which prints as > and each backspace by the similar sequence <. This makes tabs and backspaces visible.
1-9. How would you test the word count program? What are some boundaries?
1-10. Write a program which prints the words in its input, one per line.
1-11. Revise the word count program to use a better definition of "word," for example, a sequence of letters, digits and apostrophes that beins with a letter.
1-12. Write a program to print a histogram of the lengths of words in its input. It is easiest to draw the histogram horizontally; a vertical orientation is more challenging.
1-13. Write a program to convert its input to lower case, using a function lower(c) which returns c if c is not a letter, and the lower case value of c if it is a letter.
1-14. Revise the main routine of the longest line program so that it will correctly print the length of arbritarily long input lines, and as much as possible of the text.
1-15. Write a program to print all lines that are longer than 80 characters.
1-18. The test in the for statement of get_line above is rather ungainly. Rewrite the program to make it clearer, but retain the same behavior at end of the file or buffer overflow. Is this behavior the most reasonable?
1-19. Write a program detab which replaces tabs in the input with the proper number of blanks to space to the next tab stop. Assume a fixed set of tab stops, say every n positions.
1-20. Write the program entab which replaces strings of blanks by the minimum number of tabs and blanks to achieve the same spacing. use the same tab stops as for detab.
1-21. Write a program to "fold" long input lines after the last non-blank character that occurs before the nth column of input, where n is a parameter. Make sure your program does something intelligent with very long lines, and if there are no blanks or tabs before the specified column.
1-22. Write a program to remove all comments from a C program. Don't forget to handle quoted strings and character constants properly.
1-23. Write a program to check a C program for rudimentary syntax errors like unbalanced parentheses, brackets and braces. Don't forget about quotes, both angle and double, and comments. (This program is hard if you do it in full generality.)

Write a C program to input two numbers from user and find their power using pow().

Input.
	Enter base: 5.
	Enter exponent: 2.
Output: 5 ^ 2 = 25.

#include <stdio.h>

{
	int c;
	while((c = getchar()) != EOF) putchar(c);
}

main() {
	int c, nl;

	nl = 0;
	while((c = getchar()) != EOF)
		if(c == ‘\n’) ++nl;
	printf(“%d\n”, nl);
}

{
	long nc;

	nc = 0;
	while(getchar() != EOF) ++nc;
	printf(“%ld\n”, nc);
}

#define YES 1
#define NO 0

{
	int c, nl, nw, nc, inword;

	inword = NO;
	nl = nw = nc = 0;

	while((c = getchar()) != EOF) {
		++nc;
		if(c == ‘\n’) ++nl;
		if(c == ‘ ‘ || c == ‘\n’ || c == ‘\t’) inword = NO;
		else if(inword == NO) {
			inword = YES;
			++nw;
		}
	}
	printf(“%d %d %d\n”, nl, nw, nc);
}

{
	double nc;
	
	for(nc = 0; getchar() != EOF; ++nc)
		;
	printf("%.0f\n", nc);
}

{
	int c, i, nwhite, nother;
	int ndigit[10];

	nwhite = nother = 0;
	for(i = 0; i < 10; ++i)
		ndigit[i] = 0;

	while((c = getchar()) != EOF)
		if(c >= '0' && c <= '9')
			++ndigit[c-'0'];
		else if(c == ' ' || c == '\n' || c == '\t')
			++nwhite;
		else
			++nother;
	printf("digits =");

	for(i = 0; i < 10; ++i)
		printf(" %d", ndigit[i]);

	printf("\nwhite space = %d, other = %d\n", nwhite, nother);
}

arguments are passed by value to functions. C implements a "call stack" where a bit of memory is allocated at each function call and C makes a copy of the values in the calling code to pass them into the called code in a way that the calling code can see the values and change their local copies without affecting the values in the calling code.

call stacks, recursive functions, arrays & structures are called by reference.

external definitions are just like the declarations used previously, but since they occur outside of functions, the variables are external -- before a function can use an external variable, the name of the variable must be made known to the function. one way is to write an extern declaration in the function.

if the external definition of a variable occurs in the source file before its use in a particular function, then there is no need for an extern declaration in the function.

if the program is on several source files, and a variable is define in, say, and used in file2, then an extern declaration is needed in file2 to connect the two occurrences of the variable.

main() {
	int i;

	for(i = 0; i < 10; ++i)
		printf("%d %d %d\n", i, power(2, i), power(-3, i));
}

int power(int x, int n) {
	int i, n;

	p = 1;
	for(i = 1; i <= n; ++i)
		p = p * x;
	return p;
}

h	e	l	l	o	\n	\0

%s	expects a string.

variables in main are private or local to main -- automatic.

an alternative is to define variales which are external to all functions, that is, global variales which can be accessed by name by any function that cares to. an external variable has to be defined outside of any function; this allocates actual storage for it. the variable must also be declared in each function that wants to access it; this maybe done either by an explicit extern declaration or implicitly by context.

#include <stdio.h>

#define MAXLINE 1000

char line[MAXLINE];
char save[MAXLINE];
int max;

main() {
	int len;
	extern int max;
	extern char save[];
	max = 0;

	while((len = get_line()) > 0)
		if(len > max) {
			max = len;
			copy();
		}
	if(max > 0)
		printf("%s", save);
}

get_line() {
	int c, i;
	extern char line[];

	for(i = 0; i < MAXLINE - 1 && (c = getchar()) != EOF && c != '\n'; ++i)
		line[i] = c;

	if(c == '\n') {
		line[i] = c;
		++i;
	}
	line[i] = '\0';
	return i
}

copy() {
	int i;

	extern char line[], save[];

	i = 0;
	while((save[i] = line[i]) != '\0')
		++i;
}

Write a program to input a number and find square root of the given number.

Input. Enter any number: 9.

Output. Square root of 9 = 3.

--------------------------
Write a C program to input length and width of a rectangle and find area of the given rectangle. How to calculate area of a rectangle in C programming. Logic to find area of a rectangle whose length and width are given in C programming.
Example
Input
	Enter length: 5
	Enter width: 10
Output
	Area of rectangle = 50 sq. units

-------------------------

print pascal's triangle.
Write a C program to print pascal triangle up to n rows using loop. Logic to print Pascal triangle in C programming. How to print Pascal triangle of n rows using loop in C program.
Example
Input
	Input rows: 5
Output
				1
			1		1
		1		2		1
	1		3		3		1
1		4		6		4		1
  n
( k ) = n! / k!(n - k)!

------------------------

Write a C program to input side of an equilateral triangle from user and find area of the given triangle. How to find area of an equilateral triangle in C programming. C program to calculate area of an equilateral triangle if its side is given.
Example
Input		Enter side of the equilateral triangle: 10
Output		Area of equilateral triangle = 43.3 sq. units

-----------------------

Write a C program to input radius of a circle from user and find diameter, circumference and area of the circle. How to calculate diameter, circumference and area of a circle whose radius is given by user in C programming. Logic to find diameter, circumference and area of a circle in C.
Example
Input
	Enter radius: 10
Output
	Diameter = 20 units
	Circumference = 62.79 units
	Area = 314 sq. units

-------------------

Write a C Program to input two angles from user and find third angle of the triangle. How to find all angles of a triangle if two angles are given by user using C programming. C program to calculate the third angle of a triangle if two angles are given.
Examplelnput
	Enter first angle: 60
	Enter second angle: 80
Output
	Third angle = 40

-----------------

Write a C program to input marks of five subjects of a student and calculate total, average and percentage of all subjects. How to calculate total, average and percentage in C programming. Logic to find total, average and percentage in C program.
Example
Input
	Enter marks of five subjects: 95 76 85 90 89
Output
	Total = 435
	Average = 87
	Percentage = 87.00

---------------

Write a C program to input length in centimeter and convert it to meter and kilometer. How to convert length from centimeter to meter and kilometer in C programming. Length conversion program in C from centimeter to meter and centimeter to kilometer.
Example
Input
	Enter length in centimeter = 1000
Output
	Length in meter = 10 m
	Length in kilometer = 0.01 km

-------------

compound interest. P(1 + R/100)^T
simple interest. P * R * T / 100

Write a C program to input principle (amount), time and rate (P, T, R) and find Compound Interest. How to calculate compound interest in C programming. Logic to calculate compound interest in C program.
Example
Input
	Enter principle (amount): 1200
	Enter time: 2
	Enter rate: 5.4
Output
	Compound Interest = 1333.099243

Write a C program to input principle, time and rate (P, T, R) from user and find Simple Interest. How to calculate simple interest in C programming. Logic to find simple interest in C program
Example
Input
	Enter principle: 1200
	Enter time: 2
	Enter rate: 5.4
Output
	Simple Interest = 129.600006

--------------

Ex. Write a program to count blanks, tabs, and newlines.

Ex. Write a program to copy its input to its output, replacing each string of one or more blanks by a single blank.

Ex. Write a program to replace each tab by the three-character sequence >, backspace, -, which prints as >, and each backspace by the similar sequence <. This makes tabs and backspaces visible.


Ex. How would you test the word count program? What are some boundaries?

Ex. Write a program which prints the words in its input, one per line.

Ex. Revise the wc program to use a better definition of “word”, for example, a sequence of letters, digits, and apostrophes that begins with a letter.

The Product of the Primes
There is a cute result from number theory that states that for sufficiently large n the product of the primes less than n is less than or equal to e**n and that as n grows, this becomes a tight bound (that is, the ratio of the product of the primes to e**n gets close to 1 as n grows).
Computing a product of a large number of prime numbers can result in a very large number, which can potentially cause problems with our computation. (We will be talking about how computers deal with numbers a bit later in the term.) So we can convert the product of a set of primes into a sum of the logarithms of the primes by applying logarithms to both parts of this conjecture. In this case, the conjecture above reduces to the claim that the sum of the logarithms of all the primes less than n is less than n, and that as n grows, the ratio of this sum to n gets close to 1.
To compute a logarithm, we can use a built in mathematical functions from Python. To have access to these functions, you need to get them into your environment, which you can do by including the
from math import *
statement at the beginning of your file. This will allow you to use the function log in your code, e.g. log(2) will return the logarithm base e of the number 2.

Problem 2.
Write a program that computes the sum of the logarithms of all the primes from 2 to some number n, and print out the sum of the logs of the primes, the number n, and the ratio of these two quantities. Test this for different values of n.
You should be able to make only some small changes to your solution to Problem 1 to solve this problem as well.
Hints:
While you should see the ratio of the sum of the logs of the primes to the value n slowly get closer to 1, it does not approach this limit monotonically.

Write a program that computes and prints the 1000th prime number.
Hints:
To help you get started, here is a rough outline of the stages you should probably follow in writing your code:
1. Initialize some state variables
2. Generate all (odd) integers > 1 as candidates to be prime
3. For each candidate integer, test whether it is prime
1. One easy way to do this is to test whether any other integer > 1 evenly divides the candidate with 0 remainder. To do this, you can use modular arithmetic, for example, the expression a%b returns the remainder after dividing the integer a by the integer b.
2. You might think about which integers you need to check as divisors - certainly you don't need to go beyond the candidate you are checking, but how much sooner can you stop checking?
4. If the candidate is prime, print out some information so you know where you are in the computation, and update the state variables
5. Stop when you reach some appropriate end condition. In formulating this condition, don't forget that your program did not generate the first prime (2).

----------------------------------

Write a C program to input base and height of a triangle and find area of the given triangle. How to find area of a triangle in C programming. Logic to find area of a triangle in C program.
Example
Input
	Enter base of the triangle: 10
	Enter height of the triangle: 15
Output
	Area of the triangle = 75 sq. units

----------------------------------

Write a C program to input two numbers from user and find their power using pow() function. How to find power of a number in C programming. How to use pow() function in C programming.
Example
Input
	Enter base: 5
	Enter exponent: 2
Output
	5^2 = 25

---------------------------------

Write a C program to input length and width of a rectangle and calculate perimeter of the rectangle. How to find perimeter of a rectangle in C programming. Logic to find the perimeter of a rectangle if length and width are given in C programming.
Example
Input
	Enter length: 5
	Enter width: 10
Output
	Perimeter of rectangle = 30 units

---------------------------------

Write a C program to input number of days from user and convert it to years, weeks and days. How to convert days to years, weeks in C programming. Logic to convert days to years, weeks and days in C program.
Example
Input
	Enter days: 373
Output
	373 days = 1 year/s, 1 week/s and 1 day/s

-------------------------------

Write a C program to input two numbers and perform all arithmetic operations.
How to perform all arithmetic operation between two numbers in C programming.
C program to find sum, difference, product, quotient and modulus of two given numbers.
Example
Input
	First number: 10
	Second number: 5
Output
	Sum = 15
	Difference = 5
	Product = 50
	Quotient = 2
	Modulus = 0

------------------------------

Write a C program to input temperature in degree Fahrenheit and convert it to degree Centigrade. How to convert temperature from Fahrenheit to Celsius in C programming. C program for temperature conversion. Logic to convert temperature from Fahrenheit to Celsius in C program.
Example
Input
	Temperature in fahrenheit = 205
Output
	Temperature in celsius = 96.11 C

-----------------------------

Write a C program to input two numbers from user and calculate their sum. C program to add two numbers and display their sum as output. How to add two numbers in C programming.
Example
Input
	Input first number: 20
	Input second number: 10
Output
	Sum = 30

---------------------------

Write a C program to input temperature in Centigrade and convert to Fahrenheit.
How to convert temperature from degree centigrade to degree Fahrenheit in C programming. Logic to convert temperature from Celsius to Fahrenheit in C.
Example
Input
	Enter temperature in Celsius = 100
Output
	Temperature in Fahrenheit = 212 F

--------------------------

Write a C program to demonstrate input and output of all basic and derived types. How to use scanf() and printf() function perform input and output on primitive types in C programming.
Example
Input
	Enter a character: C
	Enter a signed short value: -32768
Output
	You entered character: 'C'
	You entered signed short: -32768


for(i = 0; i<lim-1 && (c=getchar()) != '\n' && c != EOF; ++i)
	s[i] = c;

while((c = getchar()) != EOF)


2-1. Write a loop equivalent to the for loop above without using &&.

int atoi(char s[]) {
	int i, n;

	n = 0;
	for(i = 0; s[i] >= '0' && s[i] <= '9'; ++i)
		n = 10 * n + s[i] - '0';

	return n;
}

int lower(int c) {
	if(c >= 'A' && c <= 'Z')
		return c + 'a' - 'A';
	return c;
}


implicit arithmetic conversions work much as expected. in general, if an operator like + or * which takes two operands has operands of different types, the "lower" type is promoted to the "higher" type before the operation proceeds. the result is of the higher type. more precisely, for each arithmetic operator, the following sequence of conversion rules is applied.

char and short are converted to int, and float is converted to double.

then if either operand is double, the other is converted to double, and the result is double.

otherwise if either operand is long, the other is converted to long, and the result is long.

otherwise if either operand is unsigned, the other is converted to unsigned, and the result is unsigned.

otherwise the operands must be int, and the result is int.

Notice that all float values in an expressions are converted to double; all floating point arithmetic in C is done in double precision.

2-2. Write the function htoi(s), which converts a string of hexadecimal digits into its equivalent integer value. The allowable digits are 0 through 9, a tghrough f, and A through F.

void squeeze(char s[], int c) {
	int i, j;

	for(i = j = 0; s[i] != '\0'; i++)
		if(s[i] != c) s[j++] = s[i];
	s[j] = '\0';
}

2-3. Write an alternate version of squeeze(s1, s2) which deletes each character in s1 which matches any character in the string s2.

void strcat(char s[], char t[]) {
	int i, j;

	i = j = 0;
	while(s[i] != '\0')
		i++;
	while((s[i++] = t[j++]) !- '\0') /* copy t */
		;
}

int getbits(unsigned x, unsigned p, unsigned n) {
	return ((x >> (p + 1 - n)) && ~(~0 << n));
}

2-5. Modify getbits to number bits from left to right.
2-6. Write a function wordlength() which computes the word length of the host machine, that is, the number of bits in an int. The function should be portable, in the sense that the same source code works on all machines.
2-7. Write a function rightrot(n, b) which rotates the integer n to the right by b bit positions.
2-8. Write the function invert(x, p, n) which inverts the n bits of x that begin at position p, leaving the others unchanged.

int bitcount(unsigned n) {
	int b;

	for(b = 0; n != 0; n >>= 1)
		if(n & 01)
			b++;
	return b;
}

2-9. In a 2's complement number system, x & ( x - 1) deletes the rightmost 1-bit in x. (Why?) Use this observation to write a faster version of bitcount.

a constant expression is an expression that involves only constants. such expressions are evaluated at compile time, rather than run time, and accordingly may be used in any place that a constant may be.

int strlen(char s[]) {
	int i;

	i = 0;
	while(s[i] != '\0')
		++i;

	return i;
}

int binary(int x, int v[], int n) {
	int low, high, mid;

	low = 0;
	high = n - 1;

	while(low <= high) {
		mid = (low+high) / 2;
		if(x < v[mid])
			high = mid - 1;
		else if(x > v[mid])
			low = mid + 1;
		else /* found match */
			return mid;
	}

	return - 1;
}

3-1. Write a function expand(s, t) which converts characters like newline and tab into visible escape sequences like \n and \t as it copies the string s to t. Use a switch.
3-2. Write a function expand(s1, s2) which expands shorthand notations like a-z in the string s1 into the equivalent complete list abc...xyz in s2. Allow for letters of either case and digits. and be prepared to handle cases like a-b-c and a-z0-9 and -a-z.
3-3. In a 2's complement number representation, our version of itoa does not handle the largest negative number, that is, the value of n equal to -(2^(wordsize-1)). Explain why not. Modify it to print that value correctly, regardless of the machine it runs on.
3-4. Write an analogous function itob(n, s) which converts the unsigned integer n into a binary character representation in s. Write itoh, which converts an integer to hexadecimal representation.
3-5. Write a version of itoa which accepts three arguments instead of two. The third argument is a minimum field width; the converted number must be padded with blanks on the left if necessary to make it wide enough.
3-6. Write a program which copies its input to its output, except that it prints only one instance from each group of adjacent identical lines. (This is a simple version of the UNIX utility uniq.)

an alternative to break is to put the testing in the loop itself:

while((n = getline(line, MAXLINE)) > 0) {
	while(--n >= 0 && (line[n] == ' ' || line[n] == '\t' || line[n] == '\n'))
		;
	...
}

macro preprocessor.

file inclusion.
	#include "filename"

macro substitution.
	#define YES 1

it is also possible to define macros with arguments, so the replacement text depends on the way the macro is called.

#define max(A, B) ((A) > (B) / (A) : (B))
#define square(x) x * x

4th and final storage class -- register. declaration advises the compiler that the variable in question will be heavily used. when possible register variables are placed in machine registers. which may result in smaller and faster programs.

register int x; register char c;		// the int part may be omitted.  register can only be applied to automatic variables and to the formal parameters of a function. in this latter case, the declaration looks like

f(register int c, register in n) {
	register int i;
	...
}

#include <stdio.h>

// gcc -S n_081_081.c

int main() {
	int compute;
	register int iter;

	scanf("%d", &compute);
	printf("compute %d\n", compute);
	for(iter = 0; iter < 1000; iter++) {
		compute = (compute * 22) * 7;
		if(compute > 1000) compute = compute % 1000;
	}
	printf("compute %d\n", compute);
}

double atof(char s[]) {
	double val, power;
	int i, sign;

	for(i = 0; s[i] == ' ' || s[i] == '\n' || s[i] == '\t'; i++)
		; /* skip white space */
	sign = 1;

	if(s[i] == '+' || s[i] == '-')
		sign = (s[i++] == '+') ? 1 : -1;

	for(val = 0; s[i] >= '0' && s[i] <= '9'; i++)
		val = 10 * val + s[i] - '0';
	if(s[i] == '.')
		i++;
	for(power = 1; s[i] >= '0' && s[i] <= '9'; i++) {
		val = 10 * val + s[i] - '0';
		power *= 10;
	}

	return sign * val / power;
}

#include <stdio.h>
#define BUFSIZE 100

char buf[BUFSIZE];	/* buffer for ungetch */
int bufp = 0;		/* next free position in buf */

int getch() {
	return (bufp > 0) ? buf[--bufp] : getchar();
}

void ungetch(int c) {
	if(bufp > BUFSIZE)
		printf("ungetch: too many characters\n");
	else
		buf[bufp++] = c;
}
4-1. Write the function rindex(s, t) which returns the position of the rightmost occurrentce of t in s, or -1 if there is none.
4-3. Given the basic framework, it's straightforward to extend the calculator. Add the modulus (%) and unary minus operators. Add an "erase" command which erases the top entry on the stack. Add commands for handling variables
4-4. Write a routine ungets(s) which will push back an entire string onto the input. Should ungets know about buf and bufp, or should it just use ungetch?

4-5. Suppose that there will never be more than one character of pushback. Modify getch and ungetch accordingly.


#include <stdio.h>
#define MAXLINE 1000

void main() {
	char line[MAXLINE];
	while(get_line(line, MAXLINE) > 0)
		if(index(line, "the") >= 0)
			printf("%s", line);
}
int get_line(char s[], int lim) {
	int c, i;
	for(i = 0; i < lim - 1 && (c=getchar() != EOF && c != '\n'; ++i)
		s[i] = c;
	if(c == '\n') {
		s[i] = c;
		++i;
	}
	s[i] = '\0';

	return i;
}
int index(char s[], char t[]) {
	int i, j, k;

	for(i = 0; s[i] != '\0'; i++) {
		for(j = i, k = 0; t[k] != '\0' && s[j] == t[k]; j++, k++)
			;
		if(t[k] == '\0')
			return i;
	}

	return -1;
}

4-9. Define a macro swap(x, y) which interchanges its two int arguments. (Block structure will help.)

static variables are a third class of storage, in addition to extern and automatic.

may be either internal or external. internal static variables are local to a particular function just as automatic variables are, but unlike automatics they remain in existence rather than coming and going each time the function is activated. this means that internal static variables provide private, permanent storage in a function. character strings that appear within a function, such as the arguments of printf, are internal static.

external static is known within the remainder of the source file in which it is declared, but not in any other file. external static thus provides a way to hide names like buf and bufp in the getch-ungetch combination, which must be external so they can be shared, yet which should not be visible to users of getch and ungetch, s0 there is no possibility of conflict.

int atoi(char s[]) {
	int i, n, sign;

	for(i = 0; s[i] == ' ' || s[i] == '\n' || s[i] == '\t'; i++)
		;	/* skip white space */
	sign = 1;
	if(s[i] == '+' || s[i] == '-')
		sign = (s[i++] == '+') ? 1 : -1;
	for(n = 0; s[i] >= '0' && s[i] <= '9';i++)
		n = 10 * n +s[i] - '0';

	return sign * n;
}

4-7. Convert an integer into a string with a recursive routine.
4-8. Write a recursive version of reverse(s), which reverses the string s.

#include <stdio.h>
#define MAXLINE 1000

main() {
	int n;
	char line[MAXLINE];

	while((n = getline(line, MAXLINE)) > 0) {
		while(--n >= 0)
			if(line[n] != ' ' && line[n] != '\t' && line[n] != '\n')
				break;
		line[n + 1] = '\0';
		printf("%s\n", line);
	}
}

void itoa(int n, char s[]) {
	int i, sign;
	if((sign = n) < 0)
		n = -n;
	i = 0;
	do {
		s[i++] = n % 10 + '0';
	} while((n /= 10) > 0);
	if(sign < 0)
		s[i++] = '-';
	s[i] = '\0';
	reverse(s);
}

#include <string.h>

void reverse(char s[]) {
	int c, i, j;

	for(i = 0, j = strlen(s) - 1; i < j; i++, j--) {
		c = s[i];
		s[i] = s[j];
		s[j] = c;
	}
}

void shell(int v[], int n) {
	int gap, i, j, temp;

	for(gap = n/2; gap > 0; gap /= 2)
		for(i = gap; i < n; i++)
			for(j = i - gap; j >= 0 && v[j] > v[j + gap]; j -= gap) {
				temp = v[j];
				v[j] = v[j + gap];
				v[j + gap] = temp;
			}
}

getop(char s[], int lim) {
	int i, c;

	while((c = getch()) == ' ' || c == '\t' || c == '\n')
		;
	if(c != '.' && (c < '0' || c < '9'))
		return c;

	s[0] = c;

	for(i = 1; (c = getchar()) >= '0' && c <= '9'; i++)
		if(i < lim)
			s[i] = c;
	if(c == '.') {
		if(i < lim)
			s[i] = c;
		for(i++; (c=getchar()) >= '0' && c <= '9'; i++)
			if(i < lim)
				s[i] = c;
	}
	if(i < lim) {
		ungetch(c);
		s[i] = '\0';
		return NUMBER;
	} else {
		while(c != '\n' && c != EOF)
			c = getchar();
		s[lim-1] = '\0';
		return TOOBIG;
	}
}

double pop() {
	if(sp > 0)
		return val[--sp];
	else {
		printf("error: stack empty\n");
		clear();
		return 0;
	}
}

clear() { sp = 0; }

#include <stdio.h>
#define MAXVAL 100 /* maximum depth of val stack */

int sp = 0; /* stack pointer */
doubl val[MAXVAL];

double push(double f) { // push f onto the value stack
	if(sp < MAXVAL)
		return val[sp++] = f;
	else {
		printf("error: stack full\n");
		clear():
		return 0;
	}
}

/* binsearch:  find x in v[0] <= v[1] <= ... <= v[n−1] */
   int binsearch(int x, int v[], int n)
   {
       int low, high, mid;
       low = 0;
       high = n − 1;
       while (low <= high) {
           mid = (low+high)/2;
           if (x < v[mid])
               high = mid + 1;
           else if (x  > v[mid])
               low = mid + 1;
           else    /* found match */
return mid;
}
       return −1;   /* no match */
   }
